# MILAN WIEDEMANN

Wolfson College, Linton Road, OX2 6UD Oxford milan.wiedemann@gmail.com  $\diamond$  www.milanwiedemann.com

#### PERSONAL SUMMARY

I am a DPhil student at the University of Oxford investigating mechanisms of change in cognitive therapy for Posttraumatic Stress Disorder. My main research interest is evidence-based health care, particularly in clinical psychology. I believe in the benefits of open science practices and try to implement them in my work as much as possible. I am also enthusiastic about creative work, like filming, video editing, or photography, to communicate research outputs with the wider public.

### EDUCATION AND QUALIFICATIONS

# University of Oxford

October 2016 - Present

DPhil in Experimental Psychology

Thesis: Processes of change in cognitive therapy for Posttraumatic Stress Disorder

Supervised by Prof. Anke Ehlers and Prof. David M. Clark

# Technische Universität Braunschweig

August 2013 - September 2015

MSc in Psychology

Main focus: Clinical Psychology

### Technische Universität Braunschweig

August 2011 - September 2013

BSc in Psychology

#### University of Groningen

September 2010 - August 2011

BSc in Psychology

#### DRK-Rettungsschule Goslar

January 2011- February 2011

Rettungssanitäter (in english 'Ambulance Care Assistant')

#### CLINICAL & RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

#### University of Oxford

October 2016 - Present

Part-time Research Assistant, Oxford Centre for Anxiety Disorders and Trauma

Oxford, UK

- · Creating videos for training clinical psychologists in specialised cognitive behavioural treatments.
- · Teaching and supervising Research Assistants in filming and editing techniques.

#### University of Oxford

April 2015 - August 2016

Research Assistant, Oxford Centre for Anxiety Disorders and Trauma

Oxford, UK

- · Filming patient testimonies and videos with clinical psychologists for internet treatments.
- · Creating whiteboard videos and animating psycho-educational illustrations.
- · Uploading text, video and audio content to online therapy programmes.

#### Technische Universität Braunschweig

September 2012 - March 2015

Part-time Research Assistant, Institute of Clinical Psychology

Braunschweig, GER

- · Conducting clinical interviews with adolescents for a longitudinal study.
- · Analysing quantitative data from a longitudinal study.
- · Managing and setting up large databases for national and international research teams.

### Local Health Authority Berlin Pankow

Intern, Social Psychiatric Department

Berlin, GER

- · Conducting clinical interviews with adolescents for a longitudinal study.
- · Analysing quantitative data from a longitudinal study.
- · Managing and setting up large databases for national and international research teams.

#### TEACHING EXPERIENCE

# University of Oxford

January 2018 - February 2018

February 2012 - March 2012

Demonstrator, Department of Experimental Psychology

Oxford, UK

· Module: Psychological Disorders and Individual Differences.

### Technische Universität Braunschweig

November 2014 - March 2015

Teaching Assistant, Institute of Clinical Psychology

Braunschweig, GER

· Module: Practical Course of Psychological Diagnostics.

### Technische Universität Braunschweig

April 2014 - September 2014

Teaching Assistant, Institute of Clinical Psychology

Braunschweig, GER

· Module: Fundamentals of Psychological Diagnostics.

### Technische Universität Braunschweig

September 2012 - January 2014

Teaching Assistant, Institute of Methodology and Biopsychology

Braunschweig, GER

· Module: Laboratory Experience and Analysis with Statistical Software.

### ADDITIONAL EXPERIENCE

### University of Oxford

July 2017 - September 2017

Part-time Research Assistant, Faculty of History

Oxford, UK

· Filming and editing of the workshop 'Changing lives: Understanding what enables children growing up in adversity to thrive in modern Britain'.

### Arbeiter-Samariter-Bund Braunschweig

May 2010 - March 2015

Ambulance Care Assistant

Braunschweig, GER

- · Medical care during the qualified transport of patients.
- · First aid and emergency treatment of patients.
- · Independent ambulance coach driver in the in-house emergency centre.

# Arbeiter-Samariter-Bund Braunschweig

July 2008 - March 2009

Civilian Service

Braunschweig, GER

- · Getting trained as an 'Ambulance Care Assistant'.
- · Medical care during the qualified transport of patients.
- $\cdot$  Independent ambulance coach driver in the in-house emergency centre.

### **SCHOLARSHIPS**

#### Mental Health Research UK

May 2018

 $Travel\ Grant$ 

· Networks Summer School 2018 in Amsterdam.

### University of Oxford, Wolfson College

June 2017

Travel Grant

· Conference of the European Association for Behavioural and Cognitive Therapies in 2017.

#### Mental Health Research UK

October 2016

PhD Scholarship

· Full-time PhD scholarship for up to four years.

Erasmus plus

February 2015

Graduate Student Scholarship

· Financial support for an internship at the Oxford Centre for Anxiety Disorders and Trauma.

#### SELECTION OF PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT

# Advanced structural equation modelling

May 2018

Summer School (5 days), University of Oxford, Department of Education

### Multilevel analysis for longitudinal data

February 2016

Workshop (3 days), Universität Landau, Methodenzentrum

# Structural equation models for longitudinal data

February 2016

Workshop (2 days), Universität Landau, Methodenzentrum

#### TECHNICAL STRENGTHS

Statistical analysis & Data science Scientific writing & Office programs Video & Audio editing Driving licence R, GitHub, Mplus, JASP, Jamovi, Praat, SPSS R-Markdown, IATEX, iWork, Microsoft Office Final Cut X, Audacity, iZotope RX Clean category B

### **PUBLICATIONS & PRESENTATIONS**

#### Peer-reviewed

I] Jennifer Wild, Emma Warnock-Parkes, Nick Grey, Richard Stott, **Milan Wiedemann**, Lauren Canvin, Harriet Rankin, Emma Shepherd, Ava Forkert, David M Clark, and Anke Ehlers. "Internet-delivered cognitive therapy for PTSD: A development pilot series". In: *European Journal of Psychotraumatology* 7.1 (2016). DOI: 10.3402/ejpt.v7.31019.

#### Software

[1] Milan Wiedemann, Graham R Thew, and Richard Stott. suddengains: An R package to identify sudden gains in psychological therapies. R package version 0.0.0.9001. 2018. URL: https://github.com/milanwiedemann/suddengains.

# Selected presentations

- [1] **Milan Wiedemann**, David M Clark, and Anke Ehlers. "Predictors and processes of sudden gains in cognitive therapy for PTSD". In: *European Association for Behavioural and Cognitive Therapies*, *Ljubljana* (2017).
- [2] **Milan Wiedemann**, David M Clark, and Anke Ehlers. "Sudden gains in cognitive therapy for PTSD Can large and stable improvements between sessions help us understand how therapy works?" In: *University of Exeter, Mood Disorder Centre, The Think-Tank Seminar* (2018).